# **ALYSSA GURKAS**

## Data Analyst | Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)

(908) 397 - 2528 @ gurkasalyssa@gmail.com 🕜 linkedin.com/in/alyssa-gurkas/

O Brooklyn, NY

## **SUMMARY**

Dedicated and results-oriented data enthusiast with over four years of experience programming in R and Microsoft Power Platform, resulting in three process automations within the EPA. A pacesetter and driven contributor, dedicated to building a culture of collaboration, curiosity, and innovation.

## **EXPERIENCE**

## **Environmental Protection Specialist (Data Analyst)**

#### **EPA/Region 2, Water Division**

🗰 02/2024 - Present

New York, NY

- Project Management: Improve National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System (NPDES) permit action tracking by developing a semi-supervised topic classification model that will be used to automate data entry, saving the team ~8 hours/week.
- Data-Driven Research: Proposed and successfully secured \$90,000 in research funding to investigate PFAS contamination sources in New Jersey, leading project development and implementation to support environmental assessment and mitigation efforts.

## Program Analyst (Data Analyst)

## **EPA/Office of Research and Development (ORD)**

iii 10/2020 - 02/2024 ♀ Washington DC

- Data Integration and Innovation: Present at EPA's R User Workgroup (~250 attendees) sharing workflow of R and Qlik integration to visualize key performance indicators (KPI) of ORD tools, models, and databases.
- Performance Management: Manage annual partner satisfaction survey (~300 respondents) to evaluate the percentage of research products meeting partner needs (quality, usability, and timeliness). Develop and oversee 32 KPIs related to ORD's research programs and Agency priorities, such as the percentage of federally-funded research that is publicly available.
- Data Management and Visualization: Manage 18 datasets associated with ORD's research products and risk assessments and create dashboards to visualize KPIs using Power BI, R Shiny, and Qlik including the ORD Research Impact dashboard.

# Community and Organizational Development Facilitator

#### **Peace Corps**

**m** 06/2018 - 03/2020

- Moldova
- Facilitate STEM Education: Developed a coding club for Moldovan elementary and middle school students using material from the Scratch Foundation, improving the coding skills of ~15 students.
- Partnership Promotion: Led partnership-building and increased collaboration between community organizations to advance resource sharing within the Hincesti municipality.
- Organizational Development: Trained four organizations (temporary placement center for at risk youth, library, creative center, and middle school) on budgeting, project proposal writing, monitoring and evaluating activities, and developing strategic plans.

#### **Environmental Policy Intern**

### **County of Roanoke**

**=** 08/2017 - 05/2018

Roanoke, VA

**Geospatial Analysis**: Utilized ArcGIS to map the proposed construction routes of the Mountain Valley Pipeline (MVP) identifying which Roanoke constituents would be affected by MVP construction, increasing the County's capacity to make data-driven decisions.

## **KEY ACCOMPLISHMENTS**

#### **Automated Processes**

Improved existing processes such as ORD's customer satisfaction survey by automating the release of over 300 emails to survey respondents.

#### **Program and Project Management**

Researched the EPA's biosolids program, identifying potential risks and briefing management to ensure a clear understanding of regulatory and programmatic challenges. Insights contributed to the development of a maturity model for operational improvements.

## **Project Proposals**

Three of the four organizations within Moldova successfully received grants after training, proving their comprehension of the project planning process and improved grant writing skills.

## **STRENGTHS**



#### Resourceful programmer

Self-direct to become proficient in R and implement solutions to improve data quality, team efficiency, and data visualization.



### Strategist

Facilitate creative problem-solving and analyze complex issues by breaking them down into manageable components, resulting in a streamlined decision-making process.



#### Autodidact

Dedicated to continuous improvement and self-growth, drawn to learning, research, and advancing science to protect the environment.

## **EDUCATION**

# BS: Environmental Policy and Planning

## Virginia Tech

**#** 2018

MS: Data Science

The City University of New York

🗰 2024 - Present

## **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

R Qlik

**Microsoft Power Platform** 

Web Development

**ESRI Products** 

**SQL**